Frederick Douglass Memorial and Historical Association Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Frederick Douglass Memorial and Historical Association Records 1900-1990 1950-1980
MSS56291
Frederick Douglass Memorial and Historical Association
6,500 items
20 containers
5.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Association dedicated to preserving Douglass's home and to disseminating knowledge of African-American history. Correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports, and other records relating to the preservation of the Frederick Douglass Memorial Home, Cedar Hill, and to African-American history. Also includes official files and personal papers of past president Mary E. C. Gregory.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895.; Gregory, Mary E. C. Mary E.C. Gregory papers.
Organizations
Frederick Douglass Housing Corporation.; Frederick Douglass Memorial and Historical Association.; Frederick Douglass Memorial Home.
Subjects
African Americans--History.; African Americans--Societies, etc.; African Americans--Washington (D.C.); Memorials--Washington (D.C.)
Places
Anacostia (Washington, D.C.)--History.
Acquisition Information
The records of the Frederick Douglass Memorial and Historical Association were given to the Library by the association, by past president Mary E. C. Gregory, and by other officers between 1975 and 1990. Other gifts were presented to the Library in 1975 by the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs via Juanita Brown, president, and from the National Park Service via Edward Fitzgerald.
Transfers
A wooden plaque with an inserted medal has been transferred to the Smithsonian Institution.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the Frederick Douglass Memorial and Historical Association are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Frederick Douglass Memorial and Historical Association (FDMHA) span the years 1900-1990, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1950-1980. The collection is arranged in six series: Correspondence; Corporate Records; Miscellany; Printed Matter; Clippings; and Additions.
Based in Washington, D.C., the FDMHA was first envisioned in the will of Helen Pitts Douglass, Frederick Douglass's second wife, who bequeathed their home in Southeast Washington (Anacostia) to the American people as a memorial to her husband. It became the main function of the association to preserve the Frederick Douglass Memorial Home at Cedar Hill and to reunite surrounding lands once part of the estate into the whole of the memorial. The FDMHA also undertook to disseminate knowledge concerning Afro-American history in Washington and throughout America.
The collection includes minutes of meetings, reports, and related material not only of the FDMHA but also of the Frederick Douglass Housing Corporation, Inc. (FDHC), an organization closely allied to the association. Interaction between the two organizations, occasionally via the National Park Service, is documented throughout the records.
Much material reflects the personal interests of FDMHA's past president Mary E. C. Gregory, whose papers were intermingled among the association's records she gave to the Library. Other organizations represented among her files include the Museum of African Art (located first in a Douglass home on Capitol Hill and later a part of the Smithsonian Institution), the Douglass Glenn Gardens apartment complex, National Association of Colored Women, National Council of Negro Women, National Urban League, Anacostia Neighborhood Museum, and the Phyllis Wheatley Young Women's Christian Association in Washington, D.C.
Arrangement of the Records
This collection is arranged in six series:
Correspondence, 1921-1985
Corporate Records, 1922-1984
Miscellany, 1952-1985
Printed Matter, 1900-1985
Clippings, undated
Additions, 1900-1990
Container List
- Correspondence, 1921-1985 (Box 1-3)
  Originals and copies of letters sent and received.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1921, 1938-1969, (9 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1970-1975, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1976-1985, (7 folders) (Box 3)
- Corporate Records, 1922-1984 (Box 4-6)
  Record books, accounts, agreements, bylaws, deeds, fact sheets, incorporation papers, minutes and agendas, reports, and miscellaneous records.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Accounts (Box 4)
    - Cash book, 1953-1955 (Box 4)
    - Insurance papers, 1947-1957 (Box 4)
    - Investors Mutual, 1955-1957 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous financial records, 1940-1984 (Box 4)
    - Receipt books, 1947-1952 (Box 4)
  - Agreements, 1946-1979 (Box 4)
  - Bylaws (Box 4)
    - Frederick Douglass Housing Corp., 1976-1982 (Box 4)
    - Frederick Douglass Memorial and Historical Association, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Corporate record books (Box 5)
    - Frederick Douglass Housing Corp., 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Frederick Douglass Memorial and Historical Association, 1922-1962, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - National Association of Colored Women (Box 5)
      - 1948-1960 (Box 5)
      - 1961-1966 (Box 6)
  - Deeds, 1953, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Fact sheets, undated (Box 6)
  - Incorporation papers (Box 6)
    - Frederick Douglass Housing Corp., undated (Box 6)
    - Frederick Douglass Memorial Corp., undated (Box 6)
    - Douglass Glenn Gardens, undated (Box 6)
  - Minutes and agendas, 1949-1981, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous records, 1954-1982 (Box 6)
  - Reports, 1962-1982 (Box 6)
- Miscellany, 1952-1985 (Box 7-10)
  Biographical file, material relating to various aspects of Afro-American history, speeches and statements, programs, invitations, menus, and other miscellany.
  - Anacostia Neighborhood Museum, Washington, D.C. (Box 7)
  - Bethune, Mary McLeod (Box 7)
  - Biographical file, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - "Black Heritage 1984," festival brochure (Box 7)
  - King, Martin Luther, Jr. (Box 7)
  - Lincoln Temple United Church of Christ, annual reports, 1978 (Box 7)
  - National Association of Colored Women (Box 8)
  - National Council of Negro Women (Box 8)
  - Notes (Box 8)
  - Photographs (Box 8)
  - Phyllis Wheatley YWCA, Washington, D.C. (Box 8)
  - Play, film, and video scripts, 1952-1984 (Box 8)
  - Press releases (Box 8)
  - Programs, invitations, menus, etc., (2 folders); (4 folders) (Box 8, Box 9)
  - "Racial Inclusiveness--A Conscious Goal," by Mrs. Henry Ingraham (Box 10)
  - Resumes (Box 10)
  - Speeches and statements (Box 10)
  - YMCAs and YWCAs (Box 10)
  - General, (2 folders) (Box 10)
- Printed Matter, 1900-1985 (Box 11-16)
  Pamphlets, leaflets, magazines, books.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Afro-American history (Box 11)
  - Anacostia Neighborhood Museum, Washington, D.C., re Afro- American churches, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Bulletins and newsletter (Box 11)
  - Congressional acts, bills, and calendars, 1900-1978 (Box 11)
  - Congressional Record (Box 12)
    - Extracts, 1964-1971 (Box 12)
    - Vol. 110, No. 132, July 1, 1964 (Box 12)
    - Vol. 110, No. 133, July 2, 1964 (Box 12)
    - Vol. 115, No. 162, Oct. 6, 1969 (Box 12)
    - Vol. 115, No. 173, Oct. 23, 1969 (Box 12)
    - Vol. 125, No. 159, Nov. 13, 1979 (Box 12)
    - Vol. 129, No. 112, Aug. 2, 1983 (Box 12)
    - Vol. 129, No. 136, Oct. 18, 1983 (Box 12)
    - Vol. 129, No. 137, Oct. 19, 1983 (Box 12)
  - Delegate 1977-The First Year of the 3rd Century, guide books on historic sites (Box 13)
  - Magazines (Box 13)
    - Africa Report, 1961-1962 (Box 13)
    - Crisis, 1963-1983 (Box 13)
    - Jet, 1957-1964 (Box 13)
    - Ebony (Box 13)
      - 1965-1969 (Box 13)
      - 1980 (Box 14)
    - Historic Preservation, 1976-1977 (Box 14)
    - Life, 1965 (Box 14)
    - Look, 1961-1966 (Box 14)
    - National Notes, National Association of Colored Women's Clubs, 1954-1961 (Box 14)
    - Time, 1957-1964 (Box 14)
    - YMCA Magazine, 1958-1972 (Box 14)
  - Museum of African Art (Box 14)
  - NAACP (Box 15)
  - National Association of Colored Women's Clubs (Box 15)
  - National Council of Negro Women (Box 15)
  - National Urban League (Box 15)
  - General, (3 folders); (5 folders) (Box 15, Box 16)
- Clippings, undated (Box 17-18)
  Newspaper and magazine clippings
  - Clippings, (3 folders) (Box 17, Box 18)
- Additions, circa 1900-1990 (Box 19-20)
  Photographs, printed matter, research material, and miscellany.
  Arranged by addition.
  - Addition I, 1953-1986 (Box 19)
    - Miscellany, 1965-1982, n.d (Box 19)
    - Photographs, 1969-1986 (Box 19)
    - Printed matter, 1953-1986 (Box 19)
  - Addition II, circa 1900-1988 (Box 19)
    - Dissertation research notes and draft of "Kelly Miller" by Mary E. C. Gregory, 1942 (Box 19)
    - Miscellany, 1934-1988, (3 folders) (Box 19)
    - Photographs, circa 1900-1985 (Box 19)
  - Addition III, 1964-1990 (Box 20)
    - Miscellany, 1964-1990, (2 folders) (Box 20)